All
right, folks. We'll wait a few more
seconds then we'll begin.
Okay, let me start.
Uh we're going to continue our series of
lectures on recurrent networks
specifically sequencetose sequence
models. Can anybody remind me of what
the last topic we covered was?
What was the last topic? CTC beam
search. Right. What kind of model was
that? What kind of problem did the CTC
model tackle?
Anyone remember that? What kind of
problem did it tackle?
training without align alignment. That's
that's true. The fundamental problem of
course is one of sequencetose sequence
modeling where an input sequence goes in
and a different sequence comes out. So
speech recognition, machine translation,
dialogue system, question answering, all
of these are examples of
sequencetosequence models where one
sequence of one of data goes in and a
different sequence comes out and there's
no necessity for the two sequences to
even be the same kind of data. For
example, in speech recognition, speech
goes in and text comes out. In machine
translation, maybe English text goes in
and French comes out. In general, there
is no need for the number of symbols in
the input sequence to be the same as the
number of symbols in the output
sequence. In fact, they need not even be
synchrony between the input and output.
So what we saw in the last week was this
kind of sequence to sequence model where
there was an input sequence and an
output sequence and there was some kind
of
order correspondence between the two
meaning if you jumbled the input around
the output could be expected to move
around in exactly the same manner.
Now the ones that we are the uh
sequencetose sequence models that we're
interested in today and in the next
class are ones where this kind of uh uh
correspondence need not exist. For
example, if you were performing machine
translation, the English the input could
be in English. I ate an apple. The input
could be in German is an upill or ishaba
gig. So if I translate it like so you'll
observe that there's no direct
correspondence between the input and the
output. I becomes is 8 became harbor
gigas and it actually split into two
right and became on and up apple became
a so there's no order correspondence and
there is no onetoone correspondence
either in fact the input can look
completely unrelated to the output. For
example, if you had a dialog system
which was helping you fix your computer,
you can see you might say my screen is
blank and the response could be can you
check if your computer is plugged in. If
you look at
the models work, before we begin on
that, we're going to take a brief detour
into a very important problem that of
modeling language. So way back when
before language models became a really
big thing
uh this uh Andre Karpati put up this
little bit of code on his web page. This
is a piece of code. Can anybody
recognize this code? What does this code
look like?
Anybody want to take a guess what is
this code?
Anyone?
Well, nobody wants to take a guess. It's
purely automatically generated.
And uh well, if you want some clues, you
use the same technique to generate this
text which looks like a math paper
complete. Again, observe that this code
is complete. It has a curly braces for
open braces. The variables are all
correctly labeled. They're all
consistent. The loops are perfect. They
are consistent. and the variables that
are being used to loop on don't change
halfway through the code. This code
would compile and it would it would run.
Uh this was latte that he generated and
much the same manner. And this latte
uh compiles to give you something that
looks like a mathematical paper.
and he also generated the same technique
uh
the same technique to generate something
that looks like a Wikipedia page. So
what was the approach that he used?
Nothing like the fancy fancy models that
we see today. All of these examples were
generated blindly by a very simple
recurrent neural network consisting of
three or four layers of LSTMs. That was
it. So this one was a simple LSTM model
trained on the entire Linux source code
and then he ran it in generative mode.
What is generative mode? We will see
shortly, right? And it generates this
near perfect code. You train it on
papers and math and then you generate
stuff from it. It generates perfect
looking map and a perfect looking
Wikipedia page. So what are what is the
model doing in these cases?
In all of these cases, the model is
doing pretty much what modern large lang
large large language models do like
chart chat, GPT, claude, Gemini and
Gorac, which are a lot more
sophisticated than just a few LSTM
layers. But at the end of the day, all
of them are language models.
And so this is going to be the focus of
the next couple of lectures, modeling
language using recurren networks.
And before we even go down that line,
we'll look at the basic notion of what
it means to model language using
recurren networks, the earliest models
and some idea of embeddings. What are
embeddings?
So what is a language model? Language
models model the probability
distribution of token sequences in a
language.
Word sequences if the words are the
tokens, character sequences if
characters are tokens or whatever other
token you may choose. So these can be
used to compute the probability of a
given token sequence or to generate
sequences from the distribution of the
language.
Now when I speak of language models,
you're probably thinking of a very
specific operation and language models
and that comes from this. What the
language model actually models is this
term here. the probability of token
sequences. This token sequence could be
a sentence. It could be a paragraph. It
could be an entire book. And the
language model is literally figuring out
what is the probability that if you were
to randomly draw a sample from the
language, it's going to look like this.
But then we decompose it using B rule
and in this into this incremental
format where the probability of a token
sequence is the probability of the first
symbol in the sequence times the
probability of the second symbol given
the first symbol times the probability
of the third symbol given the first and
second symbols and so on.
So again
the key here is to realize that the
language model is actually
modeling the probability of entire
structures in the language which could
be sentences which could be paragraphs
which could be entire books.
But to make it tractable the way we do
it is by computing these probabilities
incrementally one symbol at a time. So
did this make sense what the language
model does and how your typical model
actually deals with it.
So
and you see the distinction between the
two I assume right.
So this is what we're going to focus on
this business of predicting the next
symbol given all the sequence symbols
that have occurred so far because if you
can do this then you can use this if
this method of always predicting the
next symbol which we call next symbol
prediction to in fact predict or compute
the probabilities of entire structures
of the language.
So what does next symbol prediction look
like? Suppose I were to tell you four
score in seven years. And I asked you
what is the next word? What would you
say the next word was? Anyone?
What is it? A go, right? And how did you
know it was a go? Because you heard this
in the context of the Gettysburg
address. And anytime anybody ever said
four score in seven years, the next word
that followed was always a go. Right? Or
if I were to give you a b r a h a m l i
n c o l the next character is n right.
What are you doing in both these cases?
What is the operation you just
performed?
What was it? Anybody? What would you
call it? Guess next symbol prediction.
Right? I gave you a sequence. You
predicted the next symbol. That's what
you did. And so this operation, this
business of next symbol prediction is
what you're actually using to actually
build probability distributions for the
entire language in your head. And that's
what the computer is also going to do.
So how can you do this using a computer?
For this you need a mathematical way of
representing everything. So if our units
are words then we want to represent
words in a manner that is that can be
fed to a computer and
uh so we would represent the words as
one hot vectors
for this if you have a prespecified
vocabulary you would arrange the
vocabulary in a fixed order typically a
lexical order then every word in the
vocabulary just becomes a one hot vector
which as you all know is a vector of all
zero
except a single entry which is one and
the specific entry which is one is at
the same index as the index of the word
itself in your uh lexical orders. So
arvark over here is going to be a vector
of zeros with a one in the second
position. Aon which is third in our list
would now be this vector all zeros
except a one in the third position and
so on. If you this is what you do if
your basic unit were words. If you were
modeling your language in terms of
characters and specifically if you're
doing this in terms of English
characters, English needs about 100
characters to include both lower and
uppercase and other punctuation marks
such as commas, hyphens, apostrophes,
the space, etc. So now you arrange all
of your symbols again in a uh in a
prespecified ordered ordered list and
then every symbol now becomes a one hot
vector where the one occurs in the same
position as the corresponding symbol in
your list. So there should be nothing
surprising about this. But did this make
sense to you guys? The one hot
representation.
Yeah, simple enough, right? And so now
suppose I want to perform this
operation. I give you a four score in
seven years and I want you to predict
the next word. B in general I want you I
want you to uh build a model which takes
a bunch of a sequence of words and
predicts what the next word is. Here's
what you would do.
This is a simple model where in
predicting any word we only we only
consider the previous n words. So this
is an this is an engram model. You
predict W N based on W 1 0 through W n
minus one. And the way you do it, you'd
have your model here represented by f
and the previous n words each
represented by a one hot vector are all
going to go into the model. And then the
model itself would ideally output a one
hot vector for the next word. More
realistically, it's going to output a
probability distribution over all the
words and you'd pick a word from this
distribution. So
this model making sense to everybody?
Okay. And so how would you train this
model? Simple enough. Suppose I decided
to decided to train a four a for model
and then I had something like she
uh sells
sea
shells at the seashore.
Let me write this down. It's painful. So
this one little training sentence
actually becomes a whole bunch of
training instances. So for instance, if
I decided that I'm going to predict
every word based on the previous three
words, this set of four words becomes
one training instance where these three
words would be the input and this would
be the output. Then this set of four
words would be the next next training
instance where these three words would
be the input and this would be the
output. Then this set would be the next
training instance. So this one sentence
is going to give a whole set of training
instances simply because you can chunk
out sequences where you predict the last
word based on the previous words in the
sequence. And now you can train this
model using all of these training data.
That make sense to everybody?
Yeah. So, F could be anything. It could
be just a layer, a bunch of LSTM
layers, could be a three layer network,
a four layer network or a 100 layer
network or something more complex that
we will see in the next next few
classes.
But then doing things in this very naive
manner has a problem. And the problem is
that these words are all represented as
one hot vectors. Now if I have a 100,000
words in my vocabulary,
every word is being represented using a
100,000 dimensional vector.
Is that a a uh effective use of the
space? A 100,000 dimensions is a large
large large number of dimensions. And
now if I want to add one more word to
the to the to the uh vocabulary, I'd
have to increase my dimensionality. And
now I have 100,0001 dimensions which is
which is exponentially larger than
100,000 dimensions. Adding each each
entry in the vocabulary increases the
space uh enormously. So why do we use
one hot vectors?
Why would we want to use one hot vectors
and not any other representation? For
example, if I have a vocabulary of say n
words, then using a binary
representation, I should be able to just
use log 2 n bits, right? And if I did
this, I'd get a fairly compact
representation and it's not wasteful of
space. So why the one hot
representation? Oliver says, wait a says
equal distance. Aish, can you expand on
that?
What do you mean by equal distance over
here? That is the correct answer.
So, okay, let me tell you this, right?
Your one hot vectors are all going to
lie on the axis. If I have a 100,000
vocabulary, I have a 100,000 axes. And
the only points that I'm going to be
using on the axis are these points where
one component is one and all the other
components are zero. What is the
distance between any two words in this
representation? What's the distance
between any two words? Anyone?
Is it one?
Is it is this distance one?
Come on, guys.
It's square root of two, right? So, the
distance between any two words is square
root of two. Which means that a all word
vectors are the same length. So, you're
not assigning making them shorter or
longer. Anytime you add you introduce a
length to the individual words, you're
assigning some notion of importance to
the individual words. Longer words may
be more important, shorter words may be
less important. A priority, you cannot
assign such importance. So you want to
make all the words the same length.
Second, if you arrange them in any odd
manner, the distances between the words
will depend on the representation that
you choose and you're going to enforce
some kind of notion of these two words
are closer and those words are farther
apart. And without knowing what the
earth words actually mean, it's quite
impossible for us to assign these
distance relationships. The nice thing
about the one hot representation is that
all words are the same length and it
makes no assumption about the
relationship between words. But then
this results in the dimensionality
challenge where
the dimensionality of the space blows
up. Moreover, it's extremely wasteful of
space. This vector 1 0 0 1 0 0
represents a word. But if I just add a
tiny tiny bit 10 to -7 to this point, it
doesn't represent anything. Right? So
the actual volume of the space that
you're using that the training data is
using is just exactly zero
and it's also very very wasteful in
terms of density of points per unit
volume. It's very sparse. So what can we
do?
We can project those vectors onto a
slower dimensional plane through some
projection matrix which is a linear
transform and you can project it down to
a much much lower dimension and if you
learn this projection matrix properly.
Now in this projected down space the
vectors are not going to be all uniform
the same length and the distances
between the vectors is also no longer
going to be the same. But now if you
learn the P properly, the vectors, the
length of the vectors and their
arrangements can end up capturing
semantic relationships. Which vectors
are closer? Which vectors are farther?
Which terms group together in terms of
meaning and so on. All of this depends
on learning P properly. So how could we
learn P again? So if properly learned,
the distances between projected points
can capture semantic relationships.
But how could we learn P? Here's how we
will do it. We'll make P learnable and
then in our model, we're going to apply
the same P to each of our inputs. So the
actual vector going into this model is
not the one hot vector, but P * W. Now
observe that because W is one hot and P
is a matrix, this is this P * W is the
same as basically picking a column from
this P matrix. So here for example w0 is
just the second last has a one in the
second last position. It's the same as
saying that I'm picking the second last
vector np or equivalently we
equivalently you can also say that w0
has a vector representation that's
identical to the second last vector np.
So this is what we call an embedding
of the word. It's basically a projection
of the one hot vector onto this lower
dimensional space. And the
representation that you get for each
word in this lower dimensional space is
what you call an embedding. Did that
make sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Yeah. So now this projection
matrix can be applied to each of our
words and do that can now be fed into
the model that predicts the next word.
And of course a projection matrix is
just a matrix multiplying. It's a linear
layer and you can use the training data
as we just mentioned to learn this
matrix which is the same linear layer
applied to all the inputs along with the
components of the network itself.
And now in the in this process you have
figured out how to project your words to
a lower dimension.
This model here looks at a small set of
previous words to predict any word. So
that's a time delay neural network. Each
word is predicted using the past few
words. So here is a five gram model, a
time delay neural network where each
word is represented using the past four
words in my example.
And in this kind of a model, typically
you'd use uh an LSTN. I've forgotten to
show the recurrence, but you'd use
something like an LSTM or any other form
of recurrent neural network. And the
activations are actually no this is a
TDN there is no recurrence right so you
just use a straightup TDNN and uh the
activations you typically use in these
models are tan h we empirically found
that to be useful the output would be a
softmax
and the output of course at each point
is going to be a probability
distribution over words and in the
process of training you wanted to assign
the highest probability to the actual
next word. That's how the model would be
trained. Did all of that make sense?
Okay.
So, I got
uh I'm not sure what you mean by co.
So, now there are alternate models. This
is TDNN where you look at the past four
words and you predict the next word.
uh one hot and know there's a P over
here see all of the words are just
projected down to the uh lower dimension
right there were alternate mechanisms
proposed where people would try to
predict the central word in a bunch of
of n plus1 words so the first n /2 and
the last n /2 words would all be used to
predict the central word and once again
all the words are put through the
projection layer we're trying to learn
the p uh this was a soft bag of words
skip grams where where where where you
used a word to predict the previous n /2
words and the subsequent n over2 words.
And there were other variants that were
proposed for this uh for this model. And
the idea over here was to come up with a
mechanism for learning these projection
matrices P
because as I said if you learn them
properly then the projected down words
would actually capture semantic meaning.
And so here's this famous example from
Thomas Melo's paper in 2013 distributed
representation of words and phrases in
their compositionality
and he showed how if you actually use
these you learn the projection matrix in
this manner then the vectors in the
projected down space tend to capture
semantics. Uh here's one famous example.
He's just plotted many words, the many
uh countries and their capitals. And
you'll see that the vector that connects
China to Beijing is very similar almost
identical to the vector that connects
Russia to Moscow, Japan to Tokyo, Poland
to Warsaw, Japan, Germany to Berlin. So
in this space it has sort of learned the
notion of a country and its capital or
there was the other famous example where
he said man minus woman plus king gives
you queen because it has captured the
notion of gender.
So all things considered
learning we have looked at two things
first what is a language model? Language
model is this model which learns
probability distributions for word
sequences.
It's usually broken down into the
problem of next token prediction.
And for the next token prediction, the
tokens are represented as one hot
vectors. But this is wasteful of space.
So we first project these vectors down
to a lower dimensionality and a lower
dimensional space. And now the new
representations are what we call
embeddings. They're just obtained by
multiplying your one hot vector by a
projection matrix. And if you learn the
language model and the projection matrix
concurrently,
then the projected down vectors actually
end up capturing semantic meaning.
Did all of that make sense?
Summary. Okay, with that said, let's
give your first point.
15 seconds, guys.
Okay. Five.
Let me end the poll.
So, anybody want to answer the question
which are the
one two and three? That's right. The
distance between any two not identical
one hot vectors is the same. Words are
represented as one hot embeddings
because they do not impose any a
priority assumption about which words
are closer than others. Word embeddings
derived from LMS are lower dimensional
real value representations with the
distance between words as a meaningful
representation of their closeness. Right
now but doesn't help you find
representations for words that were not
part of your training vocabulary
now. We just saw different models. We
saw TDNNs and skip grams to learn uh uh
model language. But there the focus was
on trying to learn embeddings that
capture semantics. But if the larger
picture is to have a language model
which always predicts the next word
based on everything that's occurred in
the past, recurrence makes a lot more
sense. And so here you would have a
model which has one or more layers of
LSTM units. And of course in an LSTM you
know that the output at any time is the
probability
of output symbols given everything until
all inputs until that time. Which means
over here for example this model is
computing P P of W7 given W given W1
through W6. Here it's computing P of W10
given W1 through W9. So it actually
computes in incrementally computes the
probability of the next symbol in the
sequence as we wanted.
Now
how assuming that I have trained this
model and once again
observe that if I want to train the
model I don't need separate inputs and
outputs. I'm modeling language. So W1
through W9 are going to be is my input.
The output is the same as the input
except it's going to be W through
through W2 through W10. So I don't need
anything other than the sentences and
the language themselves to train the
model. And once I've trained the model,
how can I use it to generate new data,
new text? Here's how I do it. I could
give it an initial set of inputs and
then everything else this generates is
condition on the initial initial
subsequence. And so if I were to give it
W1 through W3, at this time the model
actually generates a probability
distribution over all the words in the
language given this initial sequence of
words. And so to obtain the next word,
you would draw a word from this
distribution that it has computed and
that's going to be the next word. And
now if you want to keep generating
stuff, that word goes back in as the
next word in the sequence. So now the
inputs are W1 through W4 at which point
it's going to compute the probability
distribution for the next word W5 from
which you draw W5 feed it back in and
keep doing this until you terminate
generation. Now where do you stop
generation?
In some cases there may be a natural
termination. For example, if you're
generating code. Now in code when you've
closed the final open race the program
is done. So you know exactly when to
start generation generation. Here this
was the example you saw earlier. This
was trained on Linux source code. It
uses a character level model predicts
character sequences and if trained
properly it correctly generates
uh functional looking code.
Here is an example where I don't think
you can hear this.
Someone just trained an LSTM on uh MIDI
from piano music. And when you run it in
generative mode, it keeps generating
very very pleasant piano music. But
there's no there's no termination
because we haven't actually indicated
how to terminate unlike in the instance
of code.
But more generally, we would like to
know when to stop termination. And you
want to know when to stop termination in
a manner that makes statistical sense in
a in a probabilistically
consistent manner. So if you keep
drawing the next word and feeding it
back in, this process would continue
till we have an appropriate way of
signaling the end.
Now beginnings and ends are not
naturally indicated in a sentence or a
word sequence. For example, if I told
you four score an eight, this four score
an eight by itself doesn't tell you
whether it's the beginning of a
sentence, whether it's the end of a
sentence or whether it's in the middle
of a sentence. We will have to make that
explicit. And so we add two additional
symbols to our vocabulary. One is a
start of sequence, a start of sentence
sentence marker. The other is an end of
sequence or end of sentence marker. So
four score and 8 has neither start of
sequence nor end of sentence
sequence. So it's the middle of a
sentence. Whereas if I had SOS four
score and 8, I've indicated that this
four is the first word in the sequence
because this this is the start of
sequence marker. So this is a fragment
from the start of a sentence. Four score
and 8 EOS. This is a terminator. It
means everything ended here. This means
that these four words represent the end
of a sentence. If I have SOS four score
and 8OS, it means the sentence is
complete. It began at four and ended at
8. Now you don't always need two
separate symbols. You could just have a
single symbol symbol S to indicate both
start and end of sentence. Sometimes we
do that. Nevertheless, the key thing is
that we need an explicit way of
indicating the starts and ends of
sentences, right? And so here,
when do we terminate?
Our model must have the end of sentence
marker as part of its vocabulary. And
you keep generating words until the word
that you drew from the output is an end
of sentence marker at which point you
you terminate your generation. You can
also do this based on other criteria
like duration and so on or length. But
keep in mind that if you're not actually
terminating it at an end of sentence
marker that is not a statistically
complete
all of that makes sense.
The start of sentence and end of
sentence markers everything that went.
Okay. So the story so far language
models model the probability of word or
symbol sequences in the language. This
is typically for performed in the form
of next symbol prediction. Given the
sequence of symbols w0 through wk. It
computes the probability distribution
for the next symbol. This can be done
using a recurren neural network. They
can be used both to compute the
probability of a symbol sequence or to
conditionally generate or extend symbol
sequence given an initial prompt.
And so that leads us to our second poll
which is here.
Can you see the poll?
10 seconds, guys.
All right,
everybody's done.
So, this was easy, but what is the
answer?
one, right? Because this is the one that
only one that has both the start of
sentence and end of sentence tagged.
So that was just a mild detour into
language modeling. But what was our
basic problem? Sequencetosequence model.
The third one is not also correct
because this is this is it doesn't have
the beginning of sentence piece. So this
is only the end of a sentence.
And
the only way to figure out the only
indicators for beginnings and ends are
the SOS and EOS markers. Nothing else.
Anyway, our problem was one of sequence
tosequence modeling. As we saw earlier,
this is the problem where some sequence
goes in and a different sequence comes
out. We saw two cases. One where there's
an order correspondence between the
input and the output. We saw this in the
we saw this in the last week. Our
current problem is one where we don't
have any assurance of any kind of
correspondence between the input and the
output. Nonetheless, we must learn to
map input sequences to output sequences.
How do we model this? For this, we going
to use this model. So, we've seen this
picture before. This is the delayed
sequence to sequence model. an input
goes in, you process the entire input
and then once you process the entire
input, you generate the output. So first
process the entire input and generate a
hidden representation for the input
subsequently.
So here's some pseudo code for it.
Remember that you're only passing things
through the hidden layer. So you go
through time at each time the network
takes the current input and the hidden
state at the previous time to generate
the next hidden state and the hidden
state at the final input is what is is
is the final hidden representation that
you get when the input has been
processed.
Subsequently this portion of the network
is going to begin operating on this
hidden input to generate the output.
So how does that work? Again, you have
this initial hidden state and
subsequently as you go through time at
each time the network can continue
operating on the hidden state. Observe
that there's no more input over here,
right? It's only operating on the hidden
state and it keeps generating the
probability distribution for the next
symbol from which
you draw the next word. You keep doing
this till the end of sequence marker has
been obtained.
So at each time the key thing is that
over here you are computing from at this
point you're computing a hidden state
and from the hidden state you're
computing a probability distribution
over symbols. And so the next word, the
next token is obtained by drawing an
entry from the probability distribution
that has been computed by the model.
You keep doing this till an end of
sequence marker has been obtained.
Did this make sense what we did over
here?
How this model works?
Okay, I see two. Okay, I'll take five.
There's something mildly broken about
this model. And what is that?
The thing is
that the output words over here, this
the actual outputs are obtained by
drawing words from these distributions.
The word that is drawn over here does
not affect the computation of the hidden
state out here. This hidden state is
only obtained from this guy. So uh for
example let's say I I got a probability
distribution over here and from this I
drew the word a.
Then can this word be apple?
Is it okay for apple to follow a? Can it
be apple?
No. Right.
So I see one no. What about the rest of
you guys? Do you agree that it's not
it's it's a no or or can it be can an A
be followed by an apple? What do you
think guys?
No. Right. On the other hand, if I do
the word and,
can I
have the word plum over here?
Could I have the word plum? No. Right.
So, here is what must happen. If I drew
the word a out here, then in this
probability distribution, the
probability of words that begin with a
wow must be high
and the probability of words that begin
with a consonant
must be low. Right?
On the other hand, if I sorry, if I drew
the word and, right? On the other hand,
if I drew the word a, then it must be
the reverse. The probability of words
that begin with a consonant must be high
and the probability of words that begin
with a vowel must be low. However,
there's no way of signaling, you know,
drawing from a distribution is a bit of
a random process. There's no way of
signaling to the model that I have drawn
an over here and so therefore wobbles
must be given uh precedence. Words that
begin with with wobbles must be given
precedence out here.
Do you see the problem?
Yes or no?
So, how would you solve this?
How would you solve this?
You can feed this output back into the
input. And now it knows that the
previous word was an A and so the word
next word must uh begin with a
consonant.
And so
this is the basic problem. If I drew a
different word out here, that word is
not fed back here for this model to know
that it must change the that the that
the next probability distribution must
change because the rec the RNN recussion
only considers the hidden state.
And so what we will do is feed the
output back into the input. This is what
I'll call a self-reference sequence
tosequence model.
So here is what the model actually looks
like. This is what I'll call the simple
translation model. It has two parts. A
first part which is a recurrent network
which operates on the input and a second
part which looks much like the model we
had here except for this loop back of
the output. And this operates on the
hidden representation
computed by this guy after it is done.
So this is the delayed self-referencing
sequencetose sequence model. Here's what
happens. You would feed the input to
this model to the to the in input
portion of the model
and it would process it until it
encountered an end of sequence marker.
At this point this hidden representation
captures stores all the information uh
information about the entire input.
Subsequently,
this portion of the model is going to
begin operating on this guy from here.
It's going to accept it and then it's
going to begin generating words in a
sequence until and output production
continues until an end of sequence
marker is generated.
So at the first time, the very first
time you have to indicate that the
sentence has begun. So maybe you so so
you would feed it a start of sequence
marker. and the hidden representation
and it's going to draw the next word.
It's going to compute a probability
distribution from which you draw the
next word that is fed back in and this
along with the hidden representation is
used to generate the next word and the
and this process continues till an end
of sentence marker is produced.
So did this make sense what we just did?
Easy, right? Observe
here that if I drew a different word
from the distribution over over here, a
different word would go in and so the
entire uh sequence that follows is going
to be modified.
Now I'm I'm using a single hidden layer
on both sides. There's no necessity.
That's just an illustration. The hidden
layer itself can be arbitrarily complex.
Uh we won't get into the complexity of
the hidden layer that highle concepts
are what are important. So I'm going to
continue illustrating things with a
single hidden layer like so. But the
discussion generalizes to more layers.
So here is how the operations would
work. Your initial input would go in and
at each time the network would take in
the latest input and the previous hidden
state and continue till the till the end
of sequence marker was obtained in the
input.
The corresponding hidden hidden state
value is the input hidden input to the
to the second portion of the network
which starts off with a startup sequence
marker and this initial hidden state and
then at each time it computes the next
hidden state and the probability
distribution
for the output. A word is drawn from
this probability distribution and that's
fed back in along with the previous
hidden state when as you uh continue to
generate outputs and this goes on until
the word that you've drawn is the end of
sequence mark.
So
headward we'll get to that right observe
that if I drew a different word over
here at the next time because the word
is going back in it's going to change
the entire output sequence.
Now we introduce terminologies.
This guy, the portion of the network
that processes the input is called the
encoder.
And the portion of the network that
captures the final representation
obtained by the encoder and then uses it
to generate the output is called a
decoder. Now my question to you guys is
have we seen something like this earlier
in in today's lecture? Have we seen
something like this earlier in today's
lecture?
the decoder part. Okay, explain. What
was that?
That's a good answer. Where did we see
this? Anybody?
Where did we see this? The language
model. This guy was just a just the
language model, was it not? This portion
was just a language model.
Yes or no?
Right?
So
the overall model it turns out is
actually just a conditional language
model. The decoder is a conditional
language model. The standard language
model computes probability of word
sequences and draws generates sequences
from this probability distribution. It
models probabilities for word sequences.
This model models the conditional
probability of word sequences. It
conditions this the language model on
the input. It is identical to the simple
LM we saw earlier. The only difference
is that the generation is now
conditioned on input from the encoder.
So this is a conditional language model.
It's a language model with the output
output being conditioned on the input.
Did that make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Can I get like 10 yeses? Okay. All
right. So,
this is our simple translation model,
right? If I want to be more detailed,
the inputs are going to be one hot
representations, but they'd be
compressed using a projection matrix
into embeddings. These embeddings can be
learned along with everything else.
And you can have different projection
matrices on the input and the output
side because these would be English,
these would be German, right? Or if
they're all the or if it's a dialog
system, they'd all be the same language.
You'd have the same projection matrix.
The key point is that you don't work on
one hot vector, you work on projected
down embeddings. Secondly, I'm not
actually going to show the P's. These
are implicit. Anytime you work on words,
you're actually working on projected
down one hot representation
representations. Secondly, here's what
we do. When the input goes in
at the very first time, what the output
the the the decoder side computes is not
a word. It computes a probability
distribution over over over words. So,
it's going to compute the probability of
all the words in the vocabulary given
the input. We are drawing a word from
this probability distribution. How many
of you know how to draw a a uh uh a
value from a category distribution?
The CS students among you must
definitely have done this as a homework
or or seen this in class, right? How
many of you know how to draw draw a
value from a category distribution?
How do you roll a virtual dice? Do you
know this?
Yes. No.
Just give me a yes, give me a no. That's
okay. Either way,
Bruno doesn't know.
Are there anyone who has encountered how
to draw dice? Do you know how to
generate a uniform random number gener
random number something between zero and
one,
right? Yes, you can just there's there's
a there's a little function called rand
which always does that. And so here's
the,
you know, it's going to give you
something between 0ero and one. So let's
say these are all probabilities P1, P2
and so on. You chunk this up. This is at
P1. This is at P1 plus P2.
This is the third one is going to be P1
plus P2 plus P3, right? And eventually
because this is the sum of all
probabilities, it's going to be one. And
then when you when you draw a uniform a
number from a uniform distribution, it's
going to fall somewhere along this line.
It might fall for example in this
location, which means that this was the
word P1, P2, P3, P4 was the word that
you that it selected. It's a very simple
process, nothing particularly
complicated, but it's very well known
how to draw a word from a category
distribution. And so
you would use that to draw the first
word that make sense at some level the
procedure
right and then that's going to go in as
the next word which takes the hidden
representation it computes a new
probability distribution from which you
draw the next word and this probability
distribution is the probability of the
second word
given the entire input
and
start of sequence
ish right in my example. So this is the
probability distribution of the second
word given this entire thing and this
input sequence. So you would draw a word
from this distribution
maybe harbor and feed it back in. And
now you would compute again a
probability distribution but this one is
the probability distribution given this
entire input and this subsequence.
And you'd continue doing this and
drawing words from these distributions
until eventually you drew an end of
sequence marker. Did that whole process
make sense?
Right. Yes. Okay.
So at each time the network produces a
probability distribution over words
given the entire input and the output
sequence so far. At each time a word is
drawn from the output distribution and
this drawn word is provided as input to
the next time. This process continues
till an end of sequence marker is drawn.
I have pseudo code for this. And this
business of drawing I've just said draw
from y of t. Right? What is this magic
operation of drawing from y of t? Now
you can draw randomly but there are
other things we can do. So
what is the
see we'll get to that right? Uh what is
our final objective if I'm if I'm
performing machine translation
if I give you an input
the model itself computes probabilities
for every single word sequence. Correct.
Can be used to compute probabilities for
every single word sequence. Yes or no?
So which of these words which of these
sequences do you want to choose? Which
word sequence do you want to choose
for this input? Do you want to choose
any odd one or do you want to choose the
word sequence that has the highest
probability? Which one would you choose?
and you add one of the highest
probability, the highest probability,
right?
So, how can you choose a word sequence
with the highest probability? Now, of
course, we know that the probability of
any word sequence is the probability of
the first word given the input times the
probability of the second word given the
input and the first word and so on. And
these guys over here, this term is
simply the probability computed for the
first word by the model. If you feed
that first word in over here, then this
is simply going to be the probability
for the second word
computed by the model given the input
and the first word. So this the
probability for a word sequence is
simply the product of the probabilities
computed for the individual words in the
sequence provided at each time the input
is the
previous sequence of words in the word
sequence that make sense
so if I want to compute the probability
of you know ABC
then I give us SOS marker it's I read
the probability of a from here then I
feed in A then I read the probability of
B from here then I feed in B then I read
the probability of C from here and then
I and then I feed in C and so on and the
product of those sequence of
probabilities is going to be the
probability of the word sequence uh
whose probability I'm trying to compute.
Did that make sense?
Right. Okay. And so I want to compute
the word sequence that has the highest
probability.
So if I want to compute the probability
of ishwise nishwon
given i8 at an apple, I'd just give it
an i8.
I'd compute the probability of ish, but
then I'd feed ish in over here. Then I'd
comput I' I' comput the probability of
Y's, but then I'd feed in Y over here
and so on to get the probability of this
word sequence. Specifically, I want to
generate the word sequence that has the
highest probability. The word sequence
that ends in an EOS and has the highest
probability. So I want to find a word
sequence so that when I feed in that
word sequence over here and read off
their probabilities and multiply them
this product is highest.
Did this operation make sense?
What I'm trying to do over here?
Yes. Right. I want to compute the word
sequence which identify the word
sequence with the highest probability.
The problem is how do you do this?
How do you draw words at each time to
get the most likely word sequence? Now,
there's a greedy answer. At each time, I
can select the most probable word. So, I
just feed something in. I pick up the
most probable word. Then, I feed that
in. I pick up the most probable word. I
feed that in. I can keep doing this. Is
that going to give me the most probable
overall word sequence? What do you guys
think? If I just keep picking the most
probable word at each time,
not necessarily, right? So why not?
Let's see an you know. So that would be
where I just do an arm max over by at
each time. This might not work because
this can cause the distribution to
become more confused at a later time.
And choosing a less likely word now
could cause the distribution at the next
time to be more peaky resulting in a
more likely overall output. Let's see an
example of how this might happen. Let's
think of an example where the sequence
that you're inputting is speech and so
you're performing speech recognition,
right? So if you're performing speech
recognition, let's say the very first
word was he. You picked it. You fed the
he back in. Then at the next location,
next time the words nose and can know,
I'm going to pronounce this with a K,
but we all know that the K is not
pronounced. These two have very similar
probabilities. But this is slightly
higher than this guy. If I were to use
greedy, then I would pick noses, right?
And so now I'm going to have he knows.
But then he knows is a very unlikely
word sequence. So what is the word that
can follow? He knows where this nose is
the nose on your face.
This there are you know there really
isn't any clear structure over here uh
to to give you any indication of what
the next word is going to be. So there
the model is going to be very confused
and going to give similar probabilities
to a whole bunch of similar low
probabilities to a whole bunch of words.
On the other hand out here if I had
chosen knows even though it was slightly
lower in probability he knows is a
structured sentence and now when you
look at the probability distribution for
the next word some words are going to
stick out compared to the others. And so
when you look at the probability of the
three-word sequence, the third word over
here, which was the outcome of confusion
because this nose doesn't really fit
with he causes the overall probability
to become really low. Whereas over here,
the fact that the third word now was
very confident means that the overall
probability was much higher. So this
guy, even though you chose a lower
probability word in the second position,
is going to have a higher overall
probability. Does that example make
sense to you guys?
Right? And so the pro problem here is
that it's impossible to know a priority
which word leads to the more promising
future. For example,
uh you know, and the effect may not be
obvious until several words down the
line.
And the choice of the wrong word early
may cumulatively lead to overall a
poorer overall score over time. So
here's an example. I just said that the
first word was he. Let's just say that
in the very first word the choices were
he and the and and the but he happened
to be slightly more probable. And then I
heard I chose he. But then if I had
chosen the instead and I'd still got
knows. The knows is a perfectly
structured sentence. So the thing that
came over here could have given you an
even higher probability output
than you know he knows blah.
So the fact that the effect of making a
choice here is only going to show up two
words or maybe 20 words down the line
cannot be known a priority. So you can't
really look ahead to decide which one to
choose. In general, making a poor choice
at any time can commit us to a very few
poor future. But at that time, you
cannot know that the choice was poor. So
how do we resolve this?
One option is to just randomly draw at
each time according to the output
probability distribution. And in
expectation, you're going to get
something that has a high probability.
And this kind of works, but it's not
optimal, right? So here, this can just
be randomly sampled,
but you're going to get a lot of very
unstructured things and it's not great.
It's not guaranteed to give you the most
likely overall output, although it may
give you something more likely than
greedy drawing. Right?
The better choice is to not make a
choice at all. But before that, here is
a poll.
Okay. 5 seconds, guys.
All right,
let's stop this here.
Okay, what are the answers?
What are the answers here?
H
someone want to give me the answers. TTF
let's see for greedy to decoding we
choose the word that has been assigned
the highest probability at each time.
True. In decoding through random
sampling we randomly choose the next
word. True. The procedure is for
randomly sampling a word has been
presented in today's class. I briefly
mentioned it but we didn't actually have
this on the slide. Right.
So what we are finding is that our
choices can get you stuck. Making a poor
choice at any time commits us to a poor
future. But you cannot know at that time
that the choice was poor. So the
solution we don't choose.
What we will do is to retain all choices
and fork the network with every possible
word as input. So here you're going to
get the probabilities for all the words.
But then you give each of these words as
input. So you make as many copies of the
network as your vocabulary and give each
of these words as input and then at each
time it's going to get a probability
distribution over all the words. So then
this guy you can use each of these words
as input and it's going to give you the
probability distribution of all words.
You can keep growing this and then the
probability dist probability for any
word sequence can be simply obtained by
multiplying the probabilities down the
chain. So here you if he went in here
you multiply the probability for he from
here. If this guy was you know nose you
multiply the you multiply in the
probability for nose from here and so
on. So you can go down the chain till
you get the probability for the entire
word sequence ending with an end of
sequence marker and then you can pick
the word sequence that has the highest
probability.
What is the problem with the solution?
Anyone? What would the problem with the
solution be?
Anybody?
It's going to go exponentially with
time, right? It's just going to blow up.
And so after t time steps, if you have a
vocabulary of size v, you'd have fork
dot v ra to t branches. That's not going
to work. And so
we're going to have we're going to
perform beam search, right? You're going
to prove at each time you just keep only
the top k scoring forks. So you say
these two guys have the highest
probability. I'm going to retain those
two guys and I'm going to clone this.
Then you get a probability distribution.
And now you choose the two top guys. But
the two top guys are not chosen simply
by picking the top one here and the top
one here. The way you would do it is to
multiply the probabilities in a
sequence. This one represents the word
sequence. He knows. This one represents
the word sequence the knows. So for to
so you you know this would be he
something. He's something else. He
knows. So you'd compute the
probabilities for all the words here
multiply by the probability for he that
you got from here. Here you do the same
but multiply by the probability for the
that you got from here. And so now you
have two V choices of which you retain
only the top two. And then those top two
are going to be fed in again. And then
you're going to get an entire
probability distribution.
And at now when you compute the
probabilities for all these guys the
probability is going to be the
probability of he times the P of P of
nose times these probabilities. Here's
going to be the probability of the times
the probability of nose times these
probabilities. You choose the entire
sequence and operate on the entire
sequence and choose the top two most
likely sequences. And so at each time
you always retain just the top two or
the top K in general and keep extending
this until you hit an end of sequence
mark. That make sense
to everybody that you're actually not
looking at the local probabilities but
the entire sequence.
Right? And if you want to compute not
just the most likely sentence but the
second most likely sentence and the
third most likely sentence and so on.
The things that have not been terminated
can be continued in the same manner. Now
often you also have to impose additional
huristics because this process biases
you towards shorter outputs which may
not always be a great thing. But this is
the overall beam search mechanism to
find the most likely output.
So I have some pseudo code for beam
search over here. I'll skip the pseudo
code. That's for your reference to make
sure that you guys have read it. We have
it in our homework. So here's your
fourth code.
10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop this
and can can give me the answers.
True false. Right. Theoretically,
correct decoding requires you to
evaluate entire the entire tree
representing every possible word
sequence. Beam search is not evaluating
the entire tree because you keep pruning
things off. So although it's better than
greedy search or something that's very
naive, it's still not optimal because in
the process of pruning, you might lose
the correct solution.
So we've seen how to perform inference,
but how do you train the model?
We must learn to make the predictions
appropriately. Remember that this is a
conditional language model. So we're
going to have to learn two things. We're
going to have to learn the parameters of
this conditional language model. You're
also going to have to learn the
parameters of this model which figures
out how to generate the conditioning
input. And all of this must be learned
to make predictions appropriately. For
example, if you're training a
translation model, it should take an I
ate an apple end of sequence and learn
to produce ishava and an upfall gig as
an ender sequence. How do you do this?
Of course, you'd initialize the
parameters of the encoder and decoder.
As always in the forward pass you would
feed the input I ate an apple end of
sequence to this guy and then from here
you' feed this and the actual target
sequence ish har and upfel gigasen out
here
and you generate outputs
and this you can compare. So you're
going to train this portion exactly like
a language model. And remember that when
you trained a language model, the way we
did it was that we gave the word
sequence and then we gave the shifted
word sequences as the target. Do you
remember that?
That's how we train a language model.
Yes. Yes or no?
Right? So you're going to do exactly
that except now you also have this guy
generating an input. And so once you do
this now you can actually compute the
divergence
exactly as you would for a language
model. And these derivatives can be
propagated back to train both update
both the parameters of this portion of
the network and this portion of the
network. Now there's something uh and if
you're doing stochastic gradient descent
very often you don't use the entire
output. just randomly choose uh even
choose words that you will use to
upgrade your update your gradients in
the output. Now there's something
fundamentally different between standard
training and this approach. Has anybody
observed that?
What is the fun what is the basic
difference?
Anyone?
You might not have observed it. So let
me say in your standard training if you
have your model your input goes in
and you get an output you compare the
output to your target output and you
train the model. Yes, yes or no?
Here is this what we're doing.
Is this what we're doing here?
We are also feeding in the output
itself. We are providing a cheat code,
right? Because observe that the output
is going into the decoder out here.
That make sense that we're doing
something different.
In your standard training, you run the
forward pass is like your standard
inference. So in your standard training,
you just give it an input
and you perform inference. You get an
output. You compare the output to your
standard target. If you did that over
here, you'd give feed an ish is I ate an
apple. Then you draw something. Maybe
instead of drawing ish over here because
the model is really poor, it got maybe,
you know, do, right? So then you'd stick
in do over here. You'd get some other
word and you keep putting these in and
the word sequence that you get over here
is could be completely unrelated to what
you actually wanted to generate. It
could be longer, shorter, it could be
any odd thing because if you ran this in
the standard inference mode, there's no
guarantee that you're going to get ish
over here. So the ish is not going to go
back here and so on.
That make sense?
I see one. Yes. What about the rest of
you guys? That makes sense to all of
you. Right here, we are feeding both the
input and the output. We're providing a
cheat code. And that's because you're
training this like a language model,
like a conditional language model. If
you train this like a regular neural
network, you just give it the input and
the output and let whatever happened
over here happen. But then in that case,
it's going to be very hard to train
because there will be no onetoone
correspondence between the desired and
actual outputs and bad things can
happen. So
the overall training given many uh
training instances each each training
instance in the forward pass you compute
the output of the network
observe both X and the desired output of
used in the forward pass. In the
backward pass you compute the divergence
between the selected words of the
desired target and the actual output.
Propagate derivatives for updates and
update parameters.
So
does this make sense to everybody what
we just did?
Okay. And so here are some examples.
Machine translation. My name is Tom. Is
it a Tom? Right. Uh I could do this for
speech recognition. The input is a
speech recording. Output could be the
English. My name is Tom. Dialogue. How I
have a problem. How may I help you?
Image to text. The input is a picture.
The output is is a caption. All of these
use the same structure. And in the
machine translation example in the
original paper by Orurin Vinol and Ilia
Satska, they showed that if you look at
this final hidden representation, it
actually captures very
useful information. It seems to capture
semantics. So here they trained a
translation model and then they looked
at the final representation for a bunch
of sentences. This is John admires Mary.
John is in love with Mary. John respects
Mary. Look at how they're all arranged
very close to each other. Mary admires
John. Mary's in love with John. Mary
respects John. These two are also
arranged. These three have just changed
the subject and the object. So they're
in a different position, but the
arrangement is roughly the same as these
three, right? And then Mary admires
John. John admires Mary to Mary admires
John. This vector is very similar to
John is in love with Mary. Mary's in
love with John. John respects Mary. Mary
respects John. So you can see how it has
also captured relationships at the
sentence level, not at the word level.
Same thing here. I was given by a a card
a card by her in the garden. In the
garden, she gave me a card. She gave me
a card in the garden.
See, just changing the manner in which
it was it was said active versus
passive. She was given a card by me in
the garden. In the garden, I gave her a
card. I gave her a card in the garden.
So these this set of three sentences and
this set of three sentences are
basically the same sentences spoken in
different voices. And you can see that
the arrangements are very similar. And
once again identical sentences seem to
have identical representations, right?
So it learns seems to learn semantics
and the original paper actually had
various examples of uh machine
translation. This was
I think from French to English.
I have no clue whether this is good or
bad because I don't know French. I'm
leaving it here because it's in the
paper but I'm told that it's really
good. Right. Uh, and then
what are those numbers on the axes? I
don't see an axis over here. But then
here's a one which was trained on a
dialogue system.
And then this is an actual output the
machine. What is the error that you're
running? Please human. I'm seeing an
error related to VPN. What is the error
message that you're getting when
connected to VPN using network connect?
Connection refused or something like
that. Right? So you can see that the
machine seems to give a response that's
not very distinguishable from a human
operator. This was one of the very first
uh large language models where we where
it was shown that the sequencetosequence
framework can actually be used to
emulate what looks like a very authentic
conversation between a human and a
machine.
So, I don't know if you're impressed or
not. I was
the same thing. Now, the encoder instead
of being a
text, it could be an image.
So, now it's not a sequence to sequence
model. It's an image tosequence model.
But the concept remains the same. You
analyze the input using a convolutional
neural network and then that that goes
in as the hidden state to your LSTM to
the language model. The language model
is still a conditional language model
except now it's conditioned on images
and uh showing this was the paper show
and tell a neural image caption
generator.
So the inference would be something like
this. The image goes in, you get a
hidden representation and then just use
that as the conditioning input to your
language model.
And here are some examples. Man in black
shirt is playing a guitar. It it's
learned from from training data. And
these captions are automatically
generated. Man in black shirt is playing
a guitar. Construction worker in orange
safety vest is working on the road. Two
young girls are playing with a Lego toy.
Boy is doing a black flip on a
wakeboard. Right. It does make some
mistakes. A young boy is holding a
baseball bat. A cat is sitting on a
couch with a remote control. A woman is
holding a teddy bear in front of a
mirror. Yeah. And this one I I never
quite understood why it saw a horse over
here. A horse is standing in the middle
of the road. But generally the this was
the first time we actually saw authentic
image captioning being produced by a
neural network uh which didn't employ a
whole lot of huristics just a
conditional language model which is very
impressive. Of course modern models are
much much better but this was the start
of it all.
Of course
uh there are some various modifications
you can do. This guy only feeds the
input to the decoder side. That means
that the input gets diluted as you go
down. So one way to get around it is to
feed this hidden representation at every
stage of the decoding. This would hold
for text. It could also hold for image
captioning. And there are other such
variants that we will see in the next
class.
This was also used shown to generate
captions for videos. So now they would
use a CNN
to generate representations for every
frame mean pull it feed it to a language
model conditional language model or
decoder and the output would be a proper
caption of the video right
so let's skip the pseudo code but that
was the that was the bulk of the story
right uh what we saw was a very simple
mechanism for
uh translating sequence to to sequences
the story is language models model the
probability of word sequences in the
language typically through an symbol
prediction. The simple sequence to
sequence model we saw can be used for
tasks such as machine translation and if
this is performed using an encoder
decoder model where the encoder extracts
feature representations for the input
symbol sequence. The decoder is a
conditional language model that uses
this representation to conditionally
generate the output statements.
Inference is performed by using
performed to find the most probable
output sequence given the input. And the
same mechanism can be used for other
kinds of conditioning like image
captional generations like image
captioning uh video captioning etc.
Right? So did all of that make sense?
Yes. Right.
There's one problem. We'll see that in
the next class. Namely that we're
placing too much emphasis on this one
hidden representation because the entire
input is packed into this guy. Can we do
better? That's in the next class. But
let me know if the lecture